<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The declaration of His Highnes William Henry, by the grace of God Prince of Orange, &amp;c. of the reasons inducing him, to appear in armes in the kingdome of England, for preserving of the Protestant religion, and for restoring the lawes and liberties of England, Scotland and Ireland.</title>
            <title>Declaration of His Highness William Henry, by the grace of God, Prince of Orange ... of the reasons inducing him to appear in arms for preserving of the Protestant religion and for restoring the laws and liberties of the ancient kingdom of Scotland</title>
            <author>William III, King of England, 1650-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96540</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2328</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220170</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578511</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578511</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172424</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96540)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172424)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2629:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The declaration of His Highnes William Henry, by the grace of God Prince of Orange, &amp;c. of the reasons inducing him, to appear in armes in the kingdome of England, for preserving of the Protestant religion, and for restoring the lawes and liberties of England, Scotland and Ireland.</title>
                  <title>Declaration of His Highness William Henry, by the grace of God, Prince of Orange ... of the reasons inducing him to appear in arms for preserving of the Protestant religion and for restoring the laws and liberties of the ancient kingdom of Scotland</title>
                  <author>William III, King of England, 1650-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Arnout Leers, by His Highnesses special order.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at the Hague :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: William Henry, Prince of Orange.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestantism.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Religion --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:172424:1"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>PROT RELIGION AND LIBERTY IE MAINTIENDRAY</head>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>THE DECLARATION OF HIS HIGHNES WILLIAM HENRY, By the Grace of God PRINCE OF ORANGE, &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub">Of the reaſons inducing him, To Appear in Armes in the Kingdome of England, for <hi>Preſerving of the Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and for <hi>Reſtoring the Lawes and Liberties</hi> of ENGLAND, SCOTLAND and IRELAND.</head>
            <p>IT is both certain, and Evident to all men, that the Publike Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and Happines of any State or Kingdome, can not be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, where the Lawes, Liberties, and Cuſtomes eſtablished, by the Lawfull authority in it, are openly Tranſgreſſed and Annulled: More eſpecially where the alteration of <hi>Religion</hi> is endeavoured, and that a <hi>Religion</hi> which is contrary to Law is endeavoured to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced: Upon which thoſe who are moſt Immediatly Concerned in it, are Indiſpenſably bound, to endeavour to Preſerve and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the eſtabliſhed Lawes Liberties and Cuſtomes: and above all the <hi>Religion</hi> and worship of God, that is Eſtablished among them: And to take ſuch an effectuall care, that the Inhabitants of the ſaid State or Kingdome, may neither be deprived of their <hi>Religion,</hi> nor of their Civill Rights. VVhich is ſo much the more Neceſſary becauſe the Greatnes and Security both of Kings, Royall families, and of all ſuch as are in Authority, as well as the Happines of their Subjects and People, depend, in a moſt eſpeciall manner, upon the exact ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and maintenance of theſe their Lawes Liberties, and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe grounds it is, that we cannot any longer forbear, to Declare that to our great regret, wee ſee that thoſe Councellours, who have now the chieffe credit with the King, have overturned the <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> Lawes, and Liberties of thoſe Realmes: and ſubjected them in all things relating to their Conſciences, Liberties, and Properties, to Arbitrary Government: and that not only by ſecret and Indirect waies, but in an open and undiſguiſed manner.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Evill Councellours for the advancing and colouring this, with ſome plauſible pretexts, did Invent and ſet on foot, the Kings <hi>Diſpencing power,</hi> by vertue of which, they pretend that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Law,</hi> he can <hi>Suſpend</hi> and <hi>Diſpence</hi> with the Execution of the <hi>Lawes,</hi> that have been enacted by the Authority, of the King and Parliament, for the ſecurity and happines of the Subject, and ſo have rendered thoſe Lawes of no effect: Tho there is nothing more certain, then that as no Lawes can be made, but by the joint concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of King and Parliament, ſo likewiſe lawes ſo enacted, which ſecure the Publike peace, and ſafety of the Nation, and the lives and liberties of every ſubject in it, can not be repealed or ſuſpended but by the ſame authority.</p>
            <p>For tho the King may pardon the punishment, that a Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour has incurred, and to which he is condemned, as in the caſes of <hi>Treaſon</hi> or <hi>Felony;</hi> yet it cannot be with any colour of reaſon, Inferred from thence, that the King can entirely ſuſpend the execution of tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Lawes, relating to <hi>Treaſon</hi> or <hi>Felony:</hi> Unleſſe it is pretended, that he is clothed with a Deſpotick and Arbitrary power, and that the Lives, Liberties, Honours and Eſtates of the Subjects, depend wholly on his good will and Pleaſure, and are entirely ſubject to him; which muſt infallibly follow, on the Kings having a power to <hi>ſuſpend</hi> the execution of the <hi>Lawes,</hi> and to diſpence with them.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Evill Councellours, in order to the giving ſome credit to this ſtrange and execrable Maxime, have ſo conducted the matter, that they have obtained a Sentence from the Judges, declaring that this <hi>Diſpencing power,</hi> is a Right belonging to the <hi>Crown;</hi> as if it were in the power of the twelve Judges, to offer up the Lawes, Rights, and Liberties, of the whole Nation, to the King, to be diſpoſed of by him Arbitrarily and at his Pleaſure and expreſſly contrary to Lawes enacted, for the ſecurity of the Subjects. In order to the obtaining this Judgment, thoſe Evill Councellours did before hand, examine ſecretly, the Opinion of the Judges, and procured ſuch of them, as could not in Conſcience concurre in ſo pernicious a Sentence, to be turned out, and others to be ſubſtituted in their Rooms till by the changes which were made, in the Courts of Judicature, they at laſt obtained that Judgment. And they have raiſed ſome to thoſe Truſts, who make open Profeſſion of the Popish Religion, tho thoſe are by Law Rendred Incapable all ſuch Employments.</p>
            <p>It is alſo Manifeſt and Notorious, that as his Majeſtie was, upon his coming to the Crown, received and acknowledged by all the ſubjects of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> as their <hi>King</hi> without the leaſt oppoſition, tho he made then open profeſſion, of the <hi>Popish Religion</hi> ſo he did then Promiſe, and Solemnly Swear, at his Coronation, that he would maintain his ſubjects, in the free enjoyment of their Lawes, and Liberties, and in particular, that he would maintain the <hi>Church of England as it was eſtablished by Law:</hi> It is likewiſe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that there have been at diverſe and ſundry times, ſeverall La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes enacted for the preſervation of thoſe Rights, and Liberties, and of the Proteſtant Religion: and among other Securities, it has been enacted that all Perſons whatſoever, that are advanced to any Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Dignity, or to bear Office in either Univerſity, as likewiſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172424:2"/>all other, that should be put in any Imployment, Civill or Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, should declare that they were not Papiſts, but were of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, and that, by their taking of the Oaths of <hi>Allegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge,</hi> and <hi>Supreamacy</hi> and the <hi>Teſt,</hi> yet theſe Evill Councellours have in effect annulled and abolished all thoſe Lawes, both with rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Eccleſiaſticall and Civill Employments.</p>
            <p>In order to Eccleſiaſticall Dignities and Offices they have not only without any colour of Law, but againſt moſt expreſſe Lawes to the contrary, ſet up a Commiſſion, of a certain Number of perſons, to whom they have committed the cogniſance and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of all Eccleſiaſticall matters: in the which Commiſſion there has been and ſtill is, one of His Majeſties Miniſters of State, who makes now publike profeſſion of the Popish Religion, and who at the time of his firſt profeſſing it, declared that for a great while be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he had beleeved that to be the only true Religion. By all this, the deplorable State to which the Proteſtant Religion is redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced is Apparent, ſince the Affairs of the Church of England, are now put into the hands of Perſons, who have accepted of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion that is manifeſty Illegal; and who have executed it contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to all Law; and that now one of their chieffe Members has abjured the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> and declared himſelfe a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> by which he is become Incapable of holding any Publike Imployment: The ſaid Commiſſioners have hitherto given ſuch proof, of their ſubmiſſion to the directions given them, that there is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to doubt, but they will ſtill continue to promote all ſuch deſigns as will be moſt aggreable to them. And thoſe Evill Councellours take care, ta raiſe none to any Eccleſiaſticall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnities, but perſons that have no zeal for the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and that now hide their unconcernednes for it, under the ſpecious pretence of <hi>Moderation.</hi> The ſaid Commiſſioners have ſuſpended the Bishop of <hi>London,</hi> only becauſe he refuſed to obey an order, that was ſent him to ſuſpend à Worthy Divine, without ſo much as citing him before him, to make his own Defence, or obſerving the common formes of Proceſſe. They have turned out a Preſident, choſen by the fellows of <hi>Magdalen Colledge,</hi> and afterwards all the Fellows of that Colledge, without ſo much as citing them before any Court that could take legall cogniſſance of that affair; or obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any Sentence againſt them by a Competent Judge. And the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reaſon, that was given, for turning them out, was their refuſing to chooſe for their Preſident; a Perſon that was recommended to them, by the Inſtigation of thoſe Evill Councellours. Tho the right of a free Election belonged undoubredly to them. But they were turned out of their freeholds, contrary to Law, and to that expreſſe proviſion in the <hi>Magna Charta; that no man shall loſe life or Goods, but by the Law of the land.</hi> And now theſe Evill Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours have put the ſaid Colledge wholly into the hands of Popiſts, tho as is aboveſaid, they are Incapable, of all ſuch Employments, both by the Law of the Land, and the ſtatutes of the Colledge. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Commiſſioners have alſo cited before them all the Chancellours and Archdeacons of England, requiring them to certifie to them the names, of all ſuch Clergymen, as have read the Kings declaration for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and of ſuch as have not read it: without conſidering that the reading of it, was not enjoined the Clergy, by the Bishops, who are their Ordinaries. The Illegality and Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency of the ſaid Court of the Eccleſiaſticall Commiſſioners, was ſo notoriouſly known, and it did ſo Evidently appear, that it tended to the Subverſion of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> that the Moſt Reverend Father in God, <hi>William</hi> Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> Primate and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan of all <hi>England,</hi> ſeeing that it was raiſed for no other end, but to oppreſſe ſuch perſons as were of Eminent Vertue, Learning, and Piety, refuſed to ſit or to concurre in it.</p>
            <p>And tho there are many expreſſe Lawes againſt all Churches or Chapells, for the exerciſe of the Popish Religion, and alſo againſt all Monaſteries and Convents, and more particularly againſt the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> yet thoſe Evill Councellours have Procured or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for the building of ſeverall Churches und Chappels, for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of that Religion: They have alſo procuted diverſe Monaſteries to be Erected, and in contempt of the Law they have not only ſet up ſeverall Colleges of <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> in diverſe places, for the corrupting of the youth, but have raiſed up one of the <hi>Order,</hi> to be a Privy Councellour and a Miniſter of State. By all which they doe evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently shew, that they are reſtrained by no rules or Law whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; but that they have ſubjected the Honours and Eſtates of the ſubjects, and the Eſtablisht Religion, to a Deſpotick power and to Arbitrary Government: In all which they are ſerved and ſeconded by thoſe Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>They have alſo followed the ſame methods with Relation to Civill affairs: For they have procured Orders, to examine all Lords Lieutenants, Deputy Lieutenants, Sheriffs, Juſtices of Peace, and all others that were in any Publike Imployment, if they would concurre with The King in the Repeal of the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Lawes:</hi> and all ſuch, whoſe Conſciences did not ſuffer them, to comply with their deſignes, were turned out; and others were put in their places, who they beleeved would be more Compliant to them; in their Deſignes of defeating the Intent and Execution of thoſe Lawes; which had been made with ſo much care and caution, for the Security of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> And in many of theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they have put profeſſed Papiſts, tho the Law has diſabled them, and warranted the ſubjects not to have any regard to their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>They have alſo invaded the Priviledges, and ſeiſed on the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of moſt of thoſe Towns that have a right to be repreſented by their Burgeſſes in Parliament: and have procured ſurrenders to be made of them, by which the Magiſtrates in them have delivered up all their Rights, and Priveledges, to be diſpoſed of, at the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of thoſe Evill Councellours: who have thereupon, placed new Magiſtrates in thoſe Towns, ſuch as they can moſt entirely confide in: and in many of them, they have put Popish Magiſtrates, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Incapacities under which the Law has put them.</p>
            <p>And wheras no Nation what ſoever can ſubſiſt without the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of good and impartiall Juſtice, upon which mens Lives, Liberties, Honours, and Eſtates, doe depend; thoſe Evill Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours have ſubjected theſe to an Arbitrary and Deſpotick power: In the moſt important affairs, they have ſtudied to diſcover before hand, the Opinions of the Judges; and have turned out ſuch, as they found would not conform themſelves to their intentions: and have put others in their places, of whom they were more aſſured, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having any regard to their abilities. And they have not ſtuck to raiſe even profeſſed Papiſts, to the Courts of Judicature, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their Incapacity by Law, and that no Regard is due to any Sentences flowing from them. They have carried this ſo far, as to deprive ſuch Judges, who in the common adminiſtration of Juſtice, shewed that they were governed by their Conſciences, and not by the directions, which the others gave them. By which it is apparent that they deſigne to render themſelves the abſolute Maſters of the Lives, Honours and Eſtates of the ſubjects, of what rank or dignity ſoever they may be: and that without having any regard either to the equity of the cauſe, or to the Conſciences of the Judges, whom they will have to ſubmit in all things, to their own will, and pleaſure: hoping by ſuch waies, to Intimidate thoſe who are yet in Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, as alſo ſuch others, as they shall think fit, to put in the Rooms of thoſe whom they have turned out; and to make them ſee, what they muſt look for, if they should at any time act in the leaſt contrary to their good liking<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and that no failings of that kind, are pardoned, in any perſons whatſoever. A great deale of blood has been shed in many places of the Kingdome, by Judges governed by thoſe Evill Councellours, againſt all the rules and forms of Law; without ſo much as ſuffering the perſons that were accuſed, to Plead in their own Defence.</p>
            <p>They have alſo, by putting the adminiſtration of juſtice, in the hands of Papiſts, brought all the matters of Civill Juſtice into great uncertainties: with how much exactnes and Juſtice ſoever that theſe Sentences may have been given. For ſince the Lawes of the Land doe not only exclude Papiſts from all places of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, but have put them under an Incapacity, none are bound to acknowledge or to obey their Judgements, and all Sentences given by them, are null and void of themſelves: ſo that all perſons who have been caſt, in Trialls before ſuch Popish Judges, may juſtly look on their Pretended Sentences, as having no more force, then the Sentences of any private and unauthoriſed perſon whatſoever. So deplorable is the caſe of the Subjects, who are obliged to anſwer to ſuch Judges, that muſt in all things ſtick to the rules, which are ſet them by thoſe Evill Councellours, who as they raiſed them up to thoſe Imployments, ſo can turn them out of them at pleaſure; and who can never be eſteemed Lawfull Judges; ſo that all their Sentences are in the Conſtruction of the law, of no Force and Efficacy. They have likewiſe diſpoſed of all Military Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in the ſame manner: For tho the Lawes have not only Excluded Papiſts, from all ſuch Imployments, but have in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, Provided that they should be Diſarmed; yet they in Contempt of theſe Lawes, have not only armed the Papiſts, but have likewiſe raiſed them up to the greateſt Military Truſts, both by Sea and Land, and that Strangers as well as Natives, and Irish as well as English, that ſo by thoſe means, having rendred themſelves Maſters both of the affairs of the Church, of the Government of the Nation, and of the courſe of Juſtice, and ſubjected them all to a Deſpotick and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary power, they might be in a Capacity to maintain and Execute their wicked deſigns, by the aſſiſtance of the Army, and thereby to enſlave the Nation.</p>
            <p>The diſmall effects of this ſubverſion of the eſtablished Religion,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172424:2"/>Lawes and Liberties in England appear more evidently to us, by what wee ſee done in Ireland: Where the whole Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is put in the hands of Papiſts, and where all the Proteſtant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants are under the daily fears of what may be juſtly apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, from the Arbitrary power which is ſet up there: which has ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de great numbers of them, leave that Kingdome and abandon their Eſtates in it, remembring well that Cruell and Bloody Maſſacre which fell out in that Iſland in the year 1641.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Evill Councellours have alſo prevailed with the King to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in Scotland that he is clothed with <hi>Abſolute power,</hi> and that all the ſubjects are bound <hi>to obey him without Reſerve:</hi> upon which he has aſſumed an Arbitrary power, both over the Religion and Lawes of that Kingdome, from all which it is Apparent, what is to be looked for in England, as ſoon as matters are duely prepared for it.</p>
            <p>Thoſe great and inſufferable Oppreſſions, and the open Contempt of all Law, together with the apprehenſions of the ſad Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that muſt certainly follow upon it, have put the ſubjects under great and juſt fears; and have made them look after ſuch lawfull Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies as are allowed of in all Nations: yet all has been without ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. And thoſe Evill Councellours have endeavoured to make all men apprehend, the loſſe of their Lives, Libertys, Honours, and Eſtates, if they should goe about to preſerve themſelves from this Oppreſſion, by Petitions, Repreſentations, or other means autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed by Law. Thus did they proceed with the Archbishop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> and the other Bishops, who having offered a moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble petition to the King, in termes full of Reſpect, and not exceding the number limited by Law, in which they ſet forth in short, the Reaſons, for which they could not obey that order, which by the Inſtigation of thoſe Evill Councellours, was ſent them, requiring them to appoint their Clergy to read in their Churches the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> were ſent to priſon and afterwards brought to a Triall, as if they had been guilty of ſome enormous Crime. They were not only obliged, to defend themſelves in that purſute, but to appear before Profeſſed Papiſts, who had not taken the Teſt and by Conſequence were men whoſe intereſt led them to condemne them: and the Judges that gave their opinion in their favours were thereupon turned out.</p>
            <p>And yet it can not be pretended, that any Kings; how great ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their power has been, and how Arbitrary and Deſpotick ſoever, they have been in the exerciſe of it, have ever reckoned it a crime for their Subjects to come, in all Submiſſion and Reſpect, and in a due number, not exceeding the limits of the Law, and repreſent to them the Reaſons that made it impoſſible for them to obey their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Thoſe Evill Councellours have alſo treated a Peer of the Realme, as a Criminall, only becauſe he ſaid that the ſubjects were not bound to obey the orders of a Popish Juſtice of Peace: tho it is Evident, that they being by Law rendred incapable of all ſuch truſts, no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard is due to their orders. This being the ſecurity which the people have by the Law for their Lives, Liberties, Honours and Eſtates, that they are not to be ſubjected to the Arbitrary procedings of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, that are contrary to Law, put into any Employments Civîll or Military.</p>
            <p>Both Wee our ſelves, and our Deareſt and moſt Entirely Beloved Conſort, the Princeſſe, have endeavoured to ſignify in termes full of reſpect, to the King the juſt and deep Regret which all theſe Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings have given us; and in Compliance with his Majeſties deſires ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnified to us, Wee Declared both by word of mouth, to his Envoy, and in writing; what our Thoughts were touching the Repealing of the <hi>Teſt and Penall Lawes;</hi> which wee did in ſuch a manner, that wee hoped wee had propoſed an Expedient, by which the Peace of thoſe Kingdomes, and a happy aggreement among the Subjects, of all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſions, might have been ſetled: but thoſe Evill Councellours, have put ſuch ill Conſtructions on theſe our good Intentions, that they have endeavoured to alienate the King more and more from us: as if Wee had deſigned, to Diſturb the quiet and Happines of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>The laſt and great Remedy for all thoſe Evills, Is <hi>the Calling of a Parliament,</hi> for ſecuring the Nation, againſt the evill practiſes of thoſe wicked Councellours: but this could not be yet compaſſed, nor can it be eaſily brought about. For thoſe men apprehending that a lawfull Parliament, being once aſſembled, they would be brought to an account, for all their open violations of Law, and for their Plots and Conſpiracies againſt the Proteſtant Religion, and the Lives and Liberties of the Subjects, they have endeavoured under the ſpecious Pretence of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> firſt to Sow diviſions among Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, between thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the Diſſenters: The deſigne being laid to engage Proteſtants; that are all equally Concerned, to pteſerve themſelves from Popish Oppreſſion; into mutuall quarrellings; that ſo by theſe, ſome advantages might be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them to bring about their Deſignes; and that both in the Election of the Members of Parliament, and afterwards in the Parliament it ſelfe. For they ſee well that if all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, could enter into a mutuall Good Underſtanding, one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Concurre together, in the Preſerving of their Religion, it would not be poſſible for them to compaſſe their wicked ends. They have alſo required all Perſons in the ſeverall Counties of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, that either were in any Imployment, or were in any Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Eſteem, to declare before hand, that they would concurre in the Repeal of the <hi>Teſt and Penael Lawes;</hi> and that they would give their voices in the Elections to Parliament, only for ſuch as would concurre in it: Such as would not thus Preingage themſelves were turned out of all Imployments: And others who entred into thoſe engagments, were put in their places, many of them being Papiſts: And contrary to the Charters and Priviledges of thoſe Burroughs, that have a Right to ſend Burgeſſes to Parliament, they have ordered ſuch Regulations to be made, as they thought fit and neceſſary, for aſſuring themſelves of all the Members, that are to be choſen by thoſe Corporations: and by this means they hope to avoid that Punishment which they have Deſerved: tho it is apparent, that all Acts made by Popish Magiſtrates are null, and Void of themſelves; So that no Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament can be Lawfull, for which the Elections and Returns are made by Popish Sheriffs and Majors of Touns; and Therefore as long as the Authority and Magiſtrary is in ſuch hands, it is not poſſible to have any Lawfull Parliament. And tho according to the Conſtitution of the English Government, and Immemoriall Cuſtome, all Elections of Parliament men ought to be made with an Entire Liberty, without any ſort of force, or the requiring the Electors to chooſe ſuch Perſons as shall be named to them, and the Perſons thus freely Elected, ought to give their Opinions freely, upon all Matters, that are brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, having the good of the Nation ever before their Eyes, and following in all things the dictates of their Conſcience, yet now the People of England can not expect a Remedy from a free Parliament, Legally Called and Choſen. But they may perhaps ſee one Called, in which all Elections will be carried by Fraud or Force, and which will be compoſed of ſuch Perſons, of whom thoſe Evill Councellours hold themſelves well aſſured, in which all things will be carried on according to their Direction and Intereſt, with out any regard to the Good or Happines of the Nation. Which may appear Evidently from this, that the ſame Perſons tried the Members of the laſt Parliament, to gain them to Conſent to the Repeal of the <hi>Teſt and Penal Lawes,</hi> and procured that Parliament to be diſſolved, when they found that they could not, neither by promiſes nor Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, Prevail with the Members to Comply with their wicked De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns.</p>
            <p>But to Crown all, there are Great and Violent Preſumptions, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing us to Beleeve, that thoſe Evill Councellours, in order to the carrying on of their ill Deſignes, and to the Gaining to themſelves the more time for the Effecting of them, for the encouraging of their Complices, and for the diſcouraging of all Good Subjects, have published that the <hi>Queen</hi> hath brought forth a <hi>Son:</hi> tho there have appeared both during the <hi>Queens</hi> pretended Bignes, and in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in which the Birth was managed, ſo many juſt and Viſible grounds of ſuſpicion, that not only wee our ſelves, but all the good Subjects of thoſe Kingdomes, doe Vehemently ſuſpect, that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Prince of <hi>Walss</hi> was not born by the <hi>Queen.</hi> And it is noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly known to all the world, that many both doubted of the Queens Bignes, and of the Birth of the Child, and yet there was not any one thing done to Satisfy them, or to put an end to their Doubts.</p>
            <p>And ſince our Deareſt and moſt Entirely Beloved Conſort, the Princeſſe, and likewiſe wee Our Selves, have ſo great an Intereſt in this Matter, and ſuch a Right, as all the world knows, to the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Crown, Since alſo the English did in the year 1672. when the States Generall of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> were Invaded, in a moſt Injuſt warre, uſe their uttermoſt Endeavours to put an end to that Warre, and that in oppoſition to thoſe who were then in the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nment: and by their ſo doing, they run the haſard, of loſing, both the favour of the Court, and their Imployments; And ſince the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Nation has ever teſtified a moſt particular Affection and Eſteem, both to pur Deareſt Conſort the Princeſſe, and to Our ſelves, WEE cannot excuſe our ſelves from eſpouſing their Intereſts, in a matter of ſuch high Conſequence, and from Contributing all that lies in us, for the Maintaining both of the Proteſtant Religion, and of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes and Liberties of thoſe Kingdomes, and for the Securing to them, the Continual Enjoyment of all their juſt Rights. To the doing of which, wee are moſt Earneſtly Solicited by a Great many Lords, both Spirituall and Temporall, and by many Gentlemen and other ſubjects of all Ranks.</p>
            <p>THEREFORE it is, that wee have thought fit, to goe over to England, and to Carry over with us a force, ſufficient by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, to defend us from the Violence of thoſe Evill Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours. AND WEE being deſirous that our Intentions in this, may
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172424:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>be Rightly Underſtood, have for this end prepared this <hi>Declaration,</hi> in which as wee have hitherto given a True Account of the Reaſons Inducing us to it, So wee now think fit to DECLARE that this our Expedition, is intended for no other Deſigne, but to have a free and lawfull Parliament aſſembled, as ſoon as is poſſible: and that in order to this, all the late Charters by which the Elections of Burgeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are limited contrary to the Ancient cuſtome, shall be conſidered as null and of no force: and likewiſe all Magiſtrates who have been Injuſtly turned out, shall forthwith reſume their former Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, as well as all the Borroughs of England shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again to their Antient Preſcriptions and Charters: And more particularly that the Ancient Charter of the Great and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous City of London, shall again be in Force: and that the Writts for the Members of Parliament shall be addreſſed to the Proper Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, according to Law and Cuſtome. That alſo none be ſuffered to chooſe or to be choſen Members of Parliament but ſuch as are quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Law: And that the Members of Parliament being thus lawfully choſen they shall meet and ſit in Full Freedome; That ſo the Two Houſes may concurre in the preparing of ſuch Lawes, as they upon full and free debate, shall Judge neceſſary and convenient, both for the confirming and executing the Law concerning the <hi>Teſt</hi> and ſuch other <hi>Lawes</hi> as are neceſſary for the Security and Maintenance of the Proteſtant Religion; as likewiſe for making ſuch Lawes as may eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish a good aggréement between the Church of England, and all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters, as alſo for the covering and ſecuring of all ſuch, who will live Peaceably under the Government as becomes good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, from all Perſecution upon the account of their Religion, even <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves not excepted; and for the doing of all other things, which the Two Houſes of Parliament shall find neceſſary for the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, Honour, and Safety of the Nation, ſo that there may be no more danger of the Nations falling at any time hereafter, under <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Government.</hi> To this Parliament wee will alſo referre the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the birth of the Pretended Prince of Wales, and of all things relating to it and to the Right of Succeſſion.</p>
            <p>And Wee for our part will concurre in every thing, that may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Peace and Happines of the Nation, which a Free and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Parliament shall determine; Since wee have nothing before our eyes in this our undertaking, but the Preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, the Covering of all men from Perſecution for their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and the Securing to the whole Nation the free enjoyment of all their Lawes, Rights and Liberties, under a Juſt and Legall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <p>This is the deſigne, that wee have Propoſed to our ſelves, in Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing upon this occaſion in Armes: In the Conduct of which, Wee will keep the Forces under our Command, under all the Strictnes of Martiall Diſcipline: and take a ſpeciall Care, that the People of the Countries thro which wee muſt march, shall not ſuffer by their means: and as ſoon as the State of the Nation will admit of it, Wee promiſe that wee will ſend back all thoſe Forreigne Forces, that wee have brought along with us.</p>
            <p>Wee doe therefore hope that all People will judge rightly of us, and approve of theſe our Proceedings: But wee chiefly rely on the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, for the ſucceſſe of this our undertaking, in which Wee place our whole and only Confidence.</p>
            <p>Wee doe in the laſt place invite and require all Perſons whatſoever, All the Peers of the Realme, both Spirituall and Temporall, all Lords Lieutenants, Deputy Lieutenants, and all Gentlemen, Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens and other Commons of all ranks, to come and aſſiſt us, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Executing of this our Deſigne; againſt all ſuch as shall En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to Oppoſe us; that ſo wee may prevent all thoſe Miſeries, which muſt needs follow upon the Nations being kept under Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Government and Slavery: And that all the Violences and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorders, which have overturned the whole Conſtitution of the English Government, may be fully redreſſed, in a FREE AND LEGALL PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>And Wee doe likewiſe reſolve that as ſoon as the Nations are brought to a ſtate of Quier, Wee will take care that a Parliament shall be called in <hi>Scotland,</hi> for the reſtoring the Ancient Conſtitution of that Kingdome, and for bringing the Matters of Religion to ſuch a Setlement, that the people may live eaſy and happy, and for put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an end to all the Injuſt Violences that have been in a courſe of ſo many years Committed there.</p>
            <p>Wee will alſo ſtudy to bring the Kingdome of <hi>Ireland</hi> to ſuch a ſtate, that the Setlement there may be Religiouſly obſerved: and that the Proteſtant and Brittish Intereſt there, may be ſecured. And wee will endeavour by all poſſible means, to procure ſuch an eſtablishment in all the Three Kingdomes that they may all live in a happy Union and Correſpondence together; and that the Proteſtant Religion, and the Peace, Honour, and Happines of thoſe Nations, may be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished upon Laſting Foundations.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under our Hand and Seal, at our Court in the Hague, <date>the Tenth day of October in the year 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>WILLIAM HENRY, PRINCE OF ORANGE. <hi>By his Highneſſes ſpeciall command</hi> C: HUYGENS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <head>His Highneſſes Additionall Declaration.</head>
            <p>AFter wee had prepared and printed this our Declaration, wee have underſtood, that the ſubverters of the Religion and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of thoſe Kingdomes, hearing of our Preparations, to aſſiſt the People againſt them, have begun to retract ſome of the Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and Deſpotick powers, that they had aſſumed, and to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſome of their Jujuſt Judgments and Decrees. The ſenſe of their Guilt, and the diſtruſt of their force, have induced them to offer to the City of London ſome ſeeming releefe from their Great Oppreſſions: hoping thereby to quiet the People, and to divert them from demanding a Secure Reeſtablishment of their Religion and Lawes under the shelter of our Armes: They doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo give out that wee Intend to Conquer and Enſlave the Nation, And therefore it is that wee have thought fit to adde a few words to our Declaration.</p>
            <p>Wee are Confident, that no perſons can have ſuch hard thought of us, as to Imagine that wee have any other Deſigne in this Undertaking, then to procure a ſetlement of the Religion and of the Liberties and Properties of the ſubjects upon ſo ſure a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, that there may be no danger of the Nations relapſing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the like miſeries at any time hereafter. And as the forces that wee have brought along with us, are utterly diſproportioned to that wicked deſigne of Conquering the Nation, if wee were Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Intending it, ſo the Great Numbers of the Principall Nobility and Gentry, that are men of Eminent Quality and Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and perſons of known Integrity and Zeal both for the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Government of England, many of them being alſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguished by their Conſtant fidelity to the Crown, who doe both accompany us in this Expedition, and have earneſtly ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us to it, will cover us from all ſuch Malicious Inſinuations: For it is not to be imagined, that either thoſe who have Invited us, or thoſe that are already come to aſſiſt us, can joyne in a wicked attempt of Conqueſt, to make void their own lawfull Titles to their Honours, Eſtates and Intereſts: Wee are alſo Confident that all men ſee how litle weight there is to be laid, on all Promiſes and Engagments that can be now made: ſince there has been ſo litle regard had in time paſt, to the moſt ſolemne Promiſes. And as that Imperfeit redreſſe that is now offered, is a plain Confeſſion of thoſe Violations of the Government that wee have ſet forth, So the Defectivenes of it is no leſſe Apparent: for they lay doune nothing which they may not take up at Pleaſure: and they reſerve entire and not ſo much as mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, their claimes and pretences to an Arbitrary and Deſpotick power; which has been the root of all their Oppreſſion, and of the totall ſubverſion of the Government. And it is plain, that the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re can be no redreſſe nor Remedy offered but in Parliament: by a Declaration of the Rights of the Subjects that have been invaded: and not by any Pretended Acts of Grace, to which the extremity of their affairs has driven them. Therefore it is that wee have thought fit to declare, that wee will referre all to a Free Aſſembly of the Nation, in a Lawfull Parliament.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under our Hand and Seal, at our Court in the Hague, <date>the 24. day of October in the year of our Lord 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>WILLIAM HENRY, PRINCE OF ORANGE. <hi>By his Highneſſes ſpeciall Command</hi> C: HUYGENS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at the Hague by ARNOUT LEERS, By his Highneſſes ſpeciall Order. 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
